Partial Register of the N. V. Borzov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
N. V. Borzov papers
1902-1984
2000C104
Hoover Institution Archives
19 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 2 scrapbooks and 36 microfilm reels (13.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, financial records, reports, memoranda, bulletins, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian students in China and the United States. Includes papers of other members of the Borzov family, and records of the Russkoe natsional'noe studencheskoe obschestvo.
Borzov, N. V.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Biographical Note
N. V. Borzov was a prominent and active figure in Russian education and émigré charitable and cultural work. Born in Glazov on 26 April 1871 (O.S.), he graduated with honors from St. Petersburg University, and entered into government service in the Ministry of Education. In 1897 he was a teacher at the Tomsk girls' high school, and in 1904 he was appointed inspector of the Tomsk Commercial School. Aside from his direct duties, he also established an evening school in Tomsk and participated in the work of societies advancing education in penitentiaries as well as in villages in the Tomsk region.
Having moved to Harbin in 1905, he was for twenty years director of the Harbin Commercial schools as well as of the education department of the Chinese Eastern Railway. At the same time, he established advanced economic and legal courses in Harbin. He was also a member of the city council. Dismissed in 1925 at the demand of the Soviet government, he moved to Berkeley, California, where his children lived. But he returned to Harbin in 1929-1931 to assume the post of director of the Kharbinskoe pervoe real'noe uchilishche. Back in California, he resumed his educational work by founding Russian kindergartens and high schools in Berkeley and San Francisco.
For many years, almost till his death on 25 November 1955, he organized the annual "Day of the Russian Child" (Den' russkogo rebenka), and edited the journal of the same name in order to raise funds and awareness of the plight of Russian children abroad.
1871 April 26 (O. S.) Born, Glazov, Russia
1897 Teacher, Mariinskaia zhenskaia gimnaziia, Tomsk, Russia
1904 Inspector, Tomskoe kommercheskoe uchilishche, Tomsk, Russia
1905-1925 Director, Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha, Harbin, China
1925 Arrived in the United States
1929-1931 Director, 1-oe Real'noe uchilishche, Harbin, China
1931 Returned to the United States Director, Obshchestvo pokrovitel'stva I prosvescheniia russkikh detei, San Francisco, California
1955 November 25 Died, Berkeley, California
Scope and Content Note
The primary individual associated with these papers is Nikolai Viktorovich Borzov, but they contain materials connected with the activities of his sons, Boris Nikolaevich and Viktor Nikolaevich Borzov, as well as materials relating to or originating from other family members: daughter Aleksandra Nikolaevna Borzov, and wife, Sofiia Aleksandrovna. Both Nikolai Viktorovich and his son, Viktor Nikolaevich, were active in a large number of organizations with social, educational, and charitable goals, particularly in connection with helping Russian children and students in China and the United States. This collection reflects their activities in this sphere. The papers are especially rich on problems of high school and university education among Russian émigrés.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
The following description includes only the microfilmed materials.
Location of Originals
In part, originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Borzov family.; Russkoe natsional'noe studencheskoe obschestvo.; China.; Education--China.; Education--United States.; Education.; Russia.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- N.V.Borzov material at the Hoover Institution (Box 1-22)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes manuscripts, newsletters, pamphlets, postcards, correspondence, and printed matter related to the Borzov family, and the Russian community in San Francisco and China.
- N.V.Borzov material at the Museum of Russian Culture (Reel 1-36)
  - BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1920-1979 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    Addresses in Borzov's honor, calling cards, clipping, family file, obituary, receipts and schedules, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
    - Addresses from students of the 1-oe Kharbinskoe russkoe real'noe uchilishche, 1930 (Folder 1: 1-2)
      General note
      See also SUBJECT FILE/ 1-oe [i.e., Pervoe] Kharbinskoe russkoe real'noe uchilishche
    - Calling cards. (Folder 1: 3)
      Some include messages to N. V. Borzov
    - Clipping about N. V. Borzov (Folder 1: 4)
    - Family file
      - Borzov, Boris Nikolaevich
        - Book, and composed of Boris Borzov's articles, poetry and notes, entitled Boris Nikolaevich Borzov, 1910-1979 (Folder 1: 5)
        - Clipping related to a polemic involving B. N. Borzov (Folder 1: 6)
      - Borzov, Viktor Nikolaevich
        - Correspondence
          - General and unidentified, 1925-1926 (Folder 1: 7)
          - Bebutova, Ol'ga, n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
        - Educational records. (Folder 1: 9)
          Includes letter of recommendation by N. V. Borzov, for admission to the University of California, 1920
    - Obituary on N. V. Borzov, written by V. N. Borzov, and published in N. P. Avtonomov, Kharbinskie kommercheskie uchilishcha, San Francisco, 1956 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Receipts (Folder 1: 11)
    - Schedules and lists of appointments (Folder 1: 12)
  - CORRESPONDENCE, 1902-1975 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence of Borzov family members. Borzov's official correspondence as director or member of various Russian organizations is located in the subject file under the organization's name
    - General, 1902-1975 and undated (Folder 2: 1)
    - Unidentified, 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 2)
    - All Cossacks' Union of San Francisco, 1951-1953 (Folder 2: 3)
    - American Association of Teachers of Slavonic and Eastern European Languages, 1945-1949
      See SUBJECT FILE
    - Antonova, Elena, 1946-1947 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Bilimovich, Aleksandr D., 1950-1954 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Brazol', Boris A.
      See Pushkin Society in America
    - Budberg, Aleksei Pavlovich, 1932-1945 and undated (Folder 2: 6)
      See also SUBJECT FILE for clippings of his newspaper articles
    - Budberg, Petr Alekseevich, 1946-1952 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Damaskin, N.
    - Daniel', Evgenii Vasil'evich, 1925-1929 and undated (Folder 2: 8)
    - Dudorov, Boris P. and N., 1935-1954 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Fedorov, Mikhail M., 1937-1940 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Gondatti, N. L., 1929 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Guins, George C., 1925-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 12)
    - Ipatieff, Vladimir N., 1946-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 13)
    - Isaenko, Evgeniia Sergeevna, 1935-1950 and undated (Folder 2: 14)
    - Karinskaia, Mariia, n.d. (Folder 2: 15)
    - Kharbinskii komitet pomoshchi russkim biezhentsam, 1929-1939 (Folder 2: 16)
      Includes receipts and clippings
    - Khorvat, Dimitrii Leonidovich, 1930-1931 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Kostriukov, Nikolai (Gen. Platoff Don Cossack Chorus), 1949-1950 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Kuchinskaia, E., 1947-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 19)
    - Kulaev, Innokentii Ivanovich, 1940-1941 and undated (Folder 2: 20)
    - Kulaev, Ivan Vasil'evich (Koulaieff), 1925-1941 and undated (Folder 2: 21)
    - Kulaev, Vladimir Petrovich and Maksimova-Kulaeva, Antonina Aleksandrovna, 1949-1953 (Folder 2: 22)
      See also SUBJECT FILE/Russian Children's Welfare Society and SUBJECT FILE/Kulaev (Koulaieff) family for third-party correspondence to the Kulaevs and biographical materials on them
      Includes third-party correspondence with the Kulaevs.
    - Kulaeva, G., 1925-1926 and undated (Folder 2: 23)
      Includes photograph of A. P. Laub dated 1918
    - Laub, Anna Pavlovna, 1940-1946 and undated (Folder 2: 24)
    - Laub, Tamara Alekseevna, 1947-1950 and undated (Folder 2: 25)
    - Lopatin, Ivan A., 1933 and undated (Folder 2: 26)
      Includes attachments: musical notes and offprint of Lopatin's article entitled "Tales From the Amur Valley," The Journal of American Folk-Lore, 1933 July-September
    - McGuire (von Arnol'd), Antonina Romanovna, 1942-1950 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Maevskii, Vladislav Al'binovich, 1946-1954 and undated (Folder 2: 28)
    - Natsional'naia organizatsiia russkikh razvedchikov, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 3: 1)
    - Nikitin, Pavel.
      See Voskhod
    - Nikolashin, G. V., 1934-1955 and undated (Folder 3: 2)
    - Noyes, George and Florence, 1928-1953 (Folder 3: 3)
      See also SUBJECT FILE/American Association of Teachers of Slavonic and East European Languages
      Attachments include: obituary of George Noyes, letter of recommendation for Borzov, and holograph by George Noyes entitled "Moia zhizn' v Imperatorskom Sankt-Peterburgskom universitete, 1898-1900," n.d.
    - Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny, 1932-1955 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Okulich, Iosif, 1936 and undated (Folder 3: 5)
    - Panina, Sofia, Countess, 1951 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Pushkin Society in America, 1936-1954 (Folder 3: 7)
      See also SUBJECT FILE/Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich
    - Riabushinskii, V. P., 1952 (Folder 3: 8)
    - Romanovskii, Sergei, Prince, 1951 (Folder 3: 9)
    - Sedykh, Mikhail D., 1940-1945 (Folder 3: 10)
    - Semchevskaia, Elena Vasil'evna, 1946-1954 and undated (Folder 3: 11)
      Includes photograph of E. V. Semchevskaia
    - Shapiro, Lazar' Solomonovich and Nadezhda, 1925-1932 and undated (Folder 3: 12)
    - Slavonic Alliance of California, 1933-1934 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Struve, Gleb Petrovich, 1948-1949 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Suvorov, A. E., n.d. (Folder 3: 15)
    - Syroboiarskii, A., 1941 and undated (Folder 3: 16)
    - Tal'berg, Nikolai D., 1949 (Folder 3: 17)
    - Tarsaidze, Aleksandr, 1947-1952 (Folder 3: 18)
    - Teffi, N., 1951 and undated (Folder 3: 19)
    - Tsurikov, N. A., 1937-1953 (Folder 3: 20)
    - Tumanov, E., n.d. (Folder 3: 21)
    - Voskhod (Pavel Nikitin), 1936-1950 and undated (Folder 3: 22)
      Includes attachments and photographs
    - Vserossiiskaia fashistskaia partiia. Kaliforniiskii otdel, 1935-1938 and undated (Folder 3: 23)
    - Zander, L. A., 1920-1947 (Folder 3: 24)
    - Zarubezhnyi soiuz russkikh voennykh invalidov. Glavnoe pravlenie, 1948 (Folder 3: 25)
    - Zaver'ialov, I., 1928-1975 (Folder 3: 26)
    - Zhelten, Elena Andreevna, 1954 and undated (Folder 3: 27)
      See also SUBJECT FILE/Russian Children's Welfare Society/ California branch
    - Miscellany. (Folder 3: 28)
      Empty envelopes
  - SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1922-1944 and undated
    Articles and letters to the editor, arranged chronologically by title
    - Letter to the editor, Russkaia zhizn', n.d. (Folder 3: 29)
      Printed copy
    - "Pamiati vydaiushchagosia ierarkha,", n.d. (Folder 3: 30)
    - "Psikhozy 1905 goda," Rossiia, n.d. (Folder 3: 31)
    - Untitled Russian language study guide.
      See SUBJECT FILE/Obshchestvo prepodavatelei russkago iazyka
    - Letters to the editor, Zaria (Harbin), [1922]. (Folder 3: 32)
      Typescript. Includes material related to the reconstruction of the Zelenyi bazar area of Harbin
    - "Opera Glinki 'Zhizn' za tsaria'," Rossiia, 1936 October 29 (Folder 3: 33)
    - "Tat'ianin den' v Peterburgie," Russkaia zhizn', 1944 January 22 (Folder 3: 34)
    - "Sibir' v 17-m viekie," Rossiia, 1944 March 9 (Folder 3: 35)
    - "Den' S.-Peterburgskago Imperatorskago universiteta," Rossiia, 1944 March 11 (Folder 3: 36)
  - RUSSKOE NATSIONAL'NOE STUDENCHESKOE OBSHCHESTVO FILE, 1920-1978 (Box 4)
    This series contains the records of the RNSO maintained by Borzov's son, Viktor Nikolaevich, who was the organization's chairman. The bulk of the records date from the first half of the 1920s. Includes clippings, correspondence, financial records, writings and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
    - General
      - Correspondence between Valentine Hayes and Aleksandra Nikolaevna Borzova regarding the transfer of the records to the Museum of Russian Culture, 1978 (Folder 4: 1)
      - Secretary's files. (Folder 4: 2-3)
        Includes minutes of meetings, correspondence, loan requests, reports and statements, applications for membership, lists, invitations and miscellaneous records
    - By-laws (Folder 4: 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Organizations.
        Includes correspondence with Ob"edinenie russkikh emigrantskikh studencheskikh organizatsii and Obshchestvo vspomoshchestvovaniia vospitannikam i vospitannitsam vysshikh uchebnykh zavedenii, and attachments
        - Undated (Folder 4: 5)
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 4: 6)
        - 1923 (Folder 4: 7)
        - 1924-1927 (Folder 4: 8)
        - 1930-1936 (Folder 4: 9)
      - Students (members and non-members) (Box 5)
        - Undated (Folder 5: 1)
        - 1920-1921 (Folder 5: 2)
        - 1922
          - January-October (Folder 5: 3)
          - November-December (Folder 5: 4)
        - 1923
          - January-February (Folder 5: 5)
          - March-April (Folder 5: 6)
          - May-June (Box-folder 6: 1)
          - July-August (Folder 6: 2)
          - September-December (Folder 6: 3)
        - 1924
          - January-April (Folder 6: 4)
          - May-December (Folder 6: 5)
        - 1925-1939 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - Financial records.
        See also Subject file/Library and bookstore for their financial statements
        For membership dues see Membership records.
        - General. (Folder 7: 2)
          Files labeled "Treasurer's records," consisting mainly of correspondence and receipts
        - Auditor's statement (Folder 7: 3)
        - Balance sheets (Folder 7: 4)
        - Donation forms (Folder 7: 5)
        - Ledgers. (Folder 7: 6-7)
          See also OVERSIZE FILE
        - Loan records. (Folder 7: 8)
          Includes statements of outstanding balances and requests for loans
        - Receipt books (Box-folder 8: 1)
        - Receipts
          - 1922 (Folder 8: 2)
          - 1923 (Folder 8: 3-4)
          - 1924 (Folder 8: 5)
          - 1925 (Folder 8: 6)
          - 1926-1941 (Box-folder 9: 1)
        - Statements (Folder 9: 2)
      - Lease (Folder 9: 3)
      - Membership records.
        Includes information on members and prospective members (newly arrived students)
        - Application forms (Folder 9: 4-6)
        - Dues records. (Folder 9: 7)
          See also Lists, qqv.
        - Information sheets on incoming Russian students from China (Folder 9: 8)
        - Lists. (Folder 9: 9)
          Includes information on payment of dues.
        - Requests for membership (Folder 9: 10)
    - Minutes of meetings
      - Undated (Folder 10: 1)
      - 1921-1922 (Folder 10: 2)
      - 1923 (Folder 10: 3)
      - 1924 (Folder 10: 4)
      - 1926-1936 (Folder 10: 5)
    - Publications
      - Biulleten' Russkago natsional'nago studencheskago obshchestva
        - Correspondence (Folder 10: 6)
        - Submissions. (Folder 10: 7-8)
          Holograph and typescript materials include information on student life in various regions, short stories and poetry
        - Printed copies (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - Russkii medved'
        - General. (Folder 11: 2)
          Correspondence and financial records
        - Submissions (Folder 11: 3-4)
        - Printed copies (Folder 11: 5)
    - Subject file.
      Includes clippings, correspondence, and other materials relating to Russian students in China, Europe, and elsewhere in the United States in the 1920s and 1930s, as well as advertisements, correspondence, financial records and other matter related to the association's annual fundraising ball
      - Library and bookstore. (Folder 11: 6-7)
        See also Financial records/General for proceeds from sales of books
        Includes catalogs, lists of books for sale and prices.
      - Mutual aid fund. (Box 12)
        See also Financial records
        - General. (Folder 12: 1)
          Organizational records and draft of by-laws
        - Questionnaire distributed to RNSO members to ascertain support for a mutual aid fund (Folder 12: 2)
      - Ob"edinenie russkikh emigrantskikh studencheskikh organizatsii, Prague, Czechoslovakia (Folder 12: 3)
      - Russian Students' Christian Association, United States (Folder 12: 4)
      - Russkii studencheskii klub, San Francisco, California (Folder 12: 5)
      - Students, Russian
        - Estonia (Folder 12: 6)
        - Harbin, China (Folder 12: 7)
      - Students' annual ball, "Tatianinskie vechera"
        - 1929-1931 (Folder 12: 8)
        - 1932-1933 (Folder 12: 9)
        - 1934 (Box-folder 13: 1)
        - 1935 (Folder 13: 2)
      - Miscellany (Folder 13: 3)
  - SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1984 (Box 13-31)
    Bulletins, clippings, correspondence, financial records, lists, memoranda, reports and other materials, arranged alphabetically by subject
    - American Association of Teachers of Slavonic and East European Languages. (Folder 13: 4)
      Includes bulletins and general correspondence
    - Budberg, Aleksei Pavlovich. (Folder 13: 5)
      See also CORRESPONDENCE for his letters to N. V. Borzov
      Clippings of his newspaper articles.
    - Bunin, Ivan A. (Folder 13: 6)
      Clipping, correspondence, notes and program relating to celebrations in his honor organized by N. V. Borzov
    - Chinese Eastern Railway. (Folder 13: 7)
      Clippings, receipts, miscellaneous documents and book entitled Sputnik zheleznodorzhnika (Harbin, 1923)
    - Cossacks (Folder 13: 8)
    - Den' russkogo rebenka (Day of the Russian Child)
      - General.
        Includes appeals, drafts of programs, invitations, lists of donors and participants, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes, reports, and other matter
        - Undated (Folder 13: 9)
        - 1932 (Folder 13: 10)
        - 1934 (Folder 13: 11)
        - 1935 (Box-folder 14: 1)
        - 1936 (Folder 14: 2)
        - 1937 (Folder 14: 3)
        - 1938 (Folder 14: 4)
        - 1940 (Folder 14: 5)
        - 1941 (Folder 14: 6)
        - 1942 (Folder 14: 7)
        - 1943 (Folder 14: 8)
        - 1944 (Folder 14: 9)
        - 1945 (Folder 14: 10)
        - 1946 (Folder 14: 11)
        - 1949-1950 (Folder 14: 12)
      - Advertisements (Folder 14: 13)
      - Clippings. (Folder 14: 14)
        Includes articles and letters to the editor by Borzov relating to Den' russkogo rebenka
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1932-1951 and undated (Folder 14: 15)
        - Alekseeva, Elizaveta Vital'evna, 1932-1936 (Folder 14: 16)
      - Financial records.
        Includes audit reports, budgets, receipts, and financial statements
        - 1932-1935 (Folder 14: 17)
        - 1936 (Folder 14: 18)
        - 1937 (Folder 14: 19)
        - 1939 (Box-folder 15: 1)
        - 1940 (Folder 15: 2)
        - 1941-1946 (Folder 15: 3)
        - 1947 (Folder 15: 4)
      - Programs (Folder 15: 5)
      - Publication-- Den' russkago rebenka
        - General. (Folder 15: 6)
          Tables of contents, financial and other records
        - Correspondence, 1930-1956 and undated (Folder 15: 7)
          See also CORRESPONDENCE for additional material mentioning Den' russkogo rebenka
          Relates primarily to submissions for publication.
        - Printed copies
          - #1 (1934)-- #7 (1940) (Folder 15: 8)
          - #8 (1941)-- #10 (1943) (Box-folder 16: 1)
          - #11 (1944)-- #12 (1945) (Folder 16: 2)
          - #13 (1946)-- #14 (1947) (Folder 16: 3)
          - #15 (1948)-- #16 (1949) (Folder 16: 4)
          - #17 (1950)-- #18 (1951) (Folder 16: 5)
          - #19 (1952)-- #20 (1953) (Box-folder 17: 1)
          - #21 (1954)-- #22 (1955) (Folder 17: 2)
        - Writings submitted for publication
          - Osorgin, Mikhail, "Zhivoi mir,", n.d. (Folder 17: 3)
            Typescript
          - Stolpe, Sven, "Nikolaj Berdjajef,", n.d. (Folder 17: 4)
      - Scrapbook. (Folder 17: 5)
        See also OVERSIZE FILE/Russian Children's Welfare Society for additional scrapbooks
      - Miscellany. (Folder 17: 6)
        Includes advertisements, clippings, programs and other matter relating to Den' celebrations in Harbin, China and New York, New York
    - Den' russkoi kul'tury (Folder 17: 7)
    - Eastern Orthodox Church Society, San Francisco, California. (Box 18)
      See Holy Trinity Cathedral
    - Education. (Folder 18: 1)
      Offprints, reports and printed matter on various aspects of education and instruction, including minutes of the Tretii Vserossiiskii s"ezd po eksperimental'noi pedagogike v Petrograde, 1916, with N. V. Borzov's notes
    - Federatsiia russkikh blagotvoritel'nykh organizatsii. (Folder 18: 2)
      Bulletins and correspondence, 1951-1954. N. V. Borzov was at one time executive director of this organization
    - Grebenshchikov, Georgii. (Folder 18: 3)
      Clippings
    - Holy Trinity Cathedral, San Francisco, California. (Folder 18: 4)
      Includes clippings on the cathedral's parochial school and the charter and other records of the Eastern Orthodox Church Society, affiliated with the cathedral
    - Institut Iapono-russkogo obshchestva, Harbin, China. (Folder 18: 5)
      Papers relating to Russian language courses offered by this institution in the 1920s include course materials and students' works
    - Khorvat, Dimitrii Leonidovich. (Folder 18: 6)
      Appeals and statements issued by Gen. Khorvat, 1918-1928
    - Khristianskii soiuz molodykh liudei, Harbin, China. (Folder 18: 7)
      Correspondence and other documents relating primarily to the founding of a "Narodnyi universitet" ("Popular University") in Harbin in the 1920s under the aegis of this organization and with the participation of N. V. Borzov
    - Komissiia po bor'be s religioznymi presledovaniiami i razrusheniem khramov v SSSR. (Folder 18: 8)
      Includes correspondence of and newspaper columns by N. V. Borzov as head of this organization, clippings, bulletins, memoranda, and other matter. Scrapbook includes materials (clippings and photographs) on émigré religious protests against the USSR in 1980, collected by Aleksandra Nikolaevna Borzova
    - Komitet po vvedeniiu russkogo iazyka v amerikanskikh uchebnykh zavedeniiakh.
      See Obshchestvo prepodavatelei russkago iazyka
    - Kruzhok truzhenikov pera, San Francisco, California (Folder 18: 9)
    - Kulaev (Koulaieff) family. (Folder 18: 10)
      Brochure entitled Ivan Vasil'evich Kulaev, clippings, including death notices, and letters to A. A. Maksimova-Kulaeva
    - Kursy perevodchikov, Harbin, China. (Folder 18: 11)
      Financial and other records
    - Kutepov, A. P. Clippings (Folder 18: 12)
    - Lermontov, Mikhail Iur'evich. (Folder 18: 13)
      Correspondence, programs and other materials relating to celebrations in his honor in 1941, organized by N. V. Borzov
    - Literaturno-khudozhestvennyi kruzhok, San Francisco, California (Folder 18: 14)
    - Mladorosskaia partiia. (Folder 18: 15)
      Programs and bulletin
    - Nikolaev, Konstantin Nikolaevich. (Folder 18: 16)
      Biographical materials
    - Ob"edinennyi komitet russkikh natsional'nykh organizatsii. (Box 19)